本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:aimie king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
Someone, save us!
誰か　助けてくれー
Right here!
承知
末吉　為吉　全力突っ張りー
Matsukichi! Tamekichi!
Full-Power Slap!
You take the weak ones!
雑魚の始末は任せたわよ
Not even good enough for a warm-up!
肩慣らしにもならねーな
Always be ready for a fight!
常駐戦陣
Who are you?
何奴だ　貴様ら
神妙にしろ　蟲共
Give it up, insects!
自分達は　蟲奉行所だ
We are the Insect Magistrate's Office!
He Shed His Skin!?
The Insect-men's True Form!!
【まさかの脱皮　蟲人の真の姿】
I've h-heard of them,
the Insect Magistrate's Office.
き　聞いた事があるぞ
蟲奉行所
江戸にある　蟲退治するための奉行所だ
They're a magisterial office in
Edo that fights the insects!
て　てことは
Wh-Which means that they didn't abandon us!
俺達は見捨てられてなかったってことだよ
お上が　俺達を助けに来てくれたんだー
The government has come to save us!
その通りです
That is correct.
我らの目的は蟲退治
Our goal is to exterminate the insects,
そして　「蟲人」真田幸村を討つこと
and kill the Insect-man Sanada Yukimura.
真田殿
Sanada-dono,
we would challenge you to combat.
我々は　あなたに真剣勝負を申し込みます
He dared...
あ奴ら
幸村様に意見を
...speak to Yukimura-sama!
勝負のルールは全てそちらにお任せします
You may decide the rules of the battle.
多数対１など　真田殿に有利に運ぶように決めていただいて結構
You may make it many versus one,
or set any terms that will confer
an advantage upon you.
我々は　これ以上民を巻き込みたくありません
We do not wish the people to suffer further!
いかがでしょう　それで黒白をつけるというのは
Why not settle things this way?
そちらにとっても悪くない話のはずです
It should be a good deal for you.
ふん　なるほど
I see.
くだらんな
Foolishness.
そのような児戯に構うほど　暇ではない
I've no time to waste on such amusements...
我々は今　罰を与えている最中だ
Right now, we are
in the midst of administering punishment.
You will be eaten, along with
those you try to protect!
貴様らも守るべき民とやらと一緒に　喰われるがいい
蟲共　仕切り直しぞ　存分に喰らうがいい
Back to it, insects...
Devour them all.
So you're running away?!
逃げるのか　貴様は
How dare you say that to Yukimura-sama—
貴様　幸村様に
待て　お館様のご指示が無い
Wait, he hasn't issued our orders.
俺が　逃げるだと
You claim that I'm running?
そうだ　お前は怖いだけだ
That's right! You're just scared!
おい　真田　あえて言わせていただく
Hey, Sanada...
I'll tell you what I think.
自分は　自分達は　お前に勝つ自信しかない
I... We...
think we can beat you with ease!
我らに　この俺に勝つ自信しかないだと
You believe
you can defeat us... Me, with ease?
Interesting...
面白い　面白いぞ貴様ら
You amuse me!
Very well...
いいぞ　その様な言葉
Never have I been told such a thing
蟲の身になってはもちろん　人の身であった時にすら言われた事は無かったぞ
since I became an insect,
or even when I was human.
今すぐこの手で　貴様らを肉塊に変えてやる
I shall tear you to shreds myself, right here!
だが　大将自らが城を下り先んじて戦っては家臣の立つ瀬が無い
However,
a lord's retainers must fight before he does,
to give them the chance to earn glory.
故に　貴様らが我が元に来るが良い
Thus, you may come to me...
屈強なる我が忠臣　十傑蟲を倒してな
By defeating my strongest retainers,
the Ten Crucifix Insects.
Sounds good to me!
望む所だ
では　始まりの鐘を鳴らそうぞ
Then I shall ring the bell,
to sound the start of battle.
Th-The mountain...
や　山が
Don't think for a second that
you'll make it to me alive.
生きて辿り着けると思うな　我が元に
それでは　参ります　皆さん
Very well, let us go...
おう
Yeah!
Up till now, there has been much
bloodshed in Kishuu Province.
これまで　この紀州藩には多くの血が流れました
皆さんの無念を晴らすため　あいつらは必ず倒します
I must win to avenge their deaths!
Our escape has been cut off.
退路は断たれましたね
退路など元よりありません　ただ進むのみです
Escape was never an option.
We must advance!
Now, then... Everything proceeds to plan.
さて　事は思惑通り進んでいます
But here is where it gets hard.
ですが　ここからです
作戦の主軸はあくまでお付きの方がいる「雪」組です
The Snow Group, with the Magistrate's servant,
is the plan's most critical component.
備前殿や岩松村の方々
Bizen-dono and the Iwamatsu villagers,
そしていろり殿の「月」組が人々を束ねます
along with Irori-dono, will lead
the people as the Moon Group.
しかし　「月」組と我ら「花」組の役目は
But the work of the Moon Group,
and those in the Flower Group,
「雪」組がお勤めを果たすまでの時間稼ぎです
is merely to buy time for the Snow
Group to complete its task.
蟲人との勝敗の決着および皆さんの生死など一切問いません
Your survival and the fight against
the Insect-men are irrelevant.
さらに「月」組も　いえ　紀州の民の全ての命に換えても
Further, the Snow Group must succeed,
even if it costs the Moon Group's lives...
「雪」組のお勤めを果たしていただけねばなりません
No, the lives of all the people in Kishuu.
それを　お忘れなく
Keep that in mind.
What's wrong, Hibachi-dono?
どうしました　火鉢殿
さっき城門をくぐってから妙な感じがするだけよ
Since we entered the castle,
I've had a strange feeling.
Ari mushicha marishiei sowaka.
アリムシ·チャー·マリシェイ·ソアカ
Wh-What?
なんだ　いきなり雲が
It turned cloudy?
どうなってんだ
What's going on?
幸村様に楯突くなどいい度胸
You have guts to challenge Yukimura-sama...
常駐戦陣
Always be ready for a fight!
懺斬り
Repentance Slash!
山茶花
Camellia Sasanqua!
末吉　為吉　全力突っ張り
Matsukichi! Tamekichi!
Full-Power Slap!
なんと
What?
幻術ですね　ここから先はどうなっているかわかりません
Illusion magic...
From here on, we don't know what we'll face.
みなさん　はぐれないように
Everyone, stay together.
はい
Right!
急ぎます
Let's hurry!
なんと　美しい
How beautiful...
え　火鉢殿　天間殿　恋川殿　大岡殿
Hibachi-dono?
Tenma-dono...
Koikawa-dono?
Oooka-dono!
あれ程はぐれてはいけないとおっしゃってたのに
After all they said about not
getting lost, they got lost...
Did Tsukishima get lost?
月島の奴　はぐれちゃったの
我らは先を急ぎます
We must hurry ahead.
火鉢殿　迷子とは情けない
Hibachi-dono!
You got lost? That's pathetic!
待っていた
I've been waiting for you.
Rat...
鼠
お主と再び相見えしこの刻を
I've been waiting endlessly for the time
when we would meet once more.
一日千秋の思いで待ってござそうろう
Ten Crucifix Insects
Nedzu Jinpachi
貴様は　関所の方々をよくも
How dare you kill those people at the gate—
我が体躯は「タガメ」でござそうろう
My body is that of a water bug.
過日は鼠共の領分「陸」で不覚を取ったら
Yesterday, we fought on land, your turf,
but the water is my territory.
水中は我が領分
水が重い　思うように刀が振れない
The water is so dense...
I can't swing my sword right.
しかも足場が無い
And there's nowhere to step.
介錯仕りそうろう
I'll slit you apart.
常駐戦陣
Always be ready for a fight!
Magnificent.
見事　我が剣圧に石垣に叩き付けられた
You allowed me to knock you into the wall
足場を確保するための策であったか
so you'd have an anchor for your sword swing?
だが鼠ごときに遅れを取る十傑蟲ではこれなくそうろう
But the Ten Crucifix Insects will
not be defeated by mere rats.
鶴翼卵の陣
Crane Wing Egg Formation!
その技は見切っている
I've already beaten that technique!
They turned into bugs?
蟲に
I wonder if Tsukishima's okay...
月島　大丈夫かな
You know him.
兄ちゃんの事だ　今頃俺達が迷子になってるって慌ててんだろ
Right now, he's probably talking
about how we got lost.
だといいんだけどね
I hope so.
皆さん　気をつけてください
Everyone, please be careful!
Okay, it's my turn now.
さて　次は拙者の出番だ
誰だ　ありゃ
Who the hell are you?
As the weaker, you must first
name yourselves... Impudent.
弱者の分際で先に名乗らぬとはなっておらん
真田十傑蟲筆頭　霧隠才蔵
I am the leader of Sanada's Ten
Crucifix Insects, Kirigakure Saizou.
拙者の名を呼ぶときは「様」をつけるのだ　クズ蟲共
When you say my name, use "-sama," maggots.
He's...
こいつが
霧隠才蔵
Kirigakure Saizou...
ひ　筆頭って　一番強いってことだよね
I-If he's the leader, wouldn't that
make him the strongest?
ちょうどいい
Perfect...
この霧隠才蔵ってやつを倒せばいいんだろう
So I just need to defeat this
Kirigakure Saizou guy, right?
なっておらん
Impudent.
I told you to use "-sama," maggot!
だから　「様」をつけ　このクズ蟲共が
何だよ　この音は
What is this sound?
み　耳が　頭が割れそう
M-My ears...
My head is splitting!
I understand...
なるほど
He must have the body of a cricket.
どうやら　やつの体躯は蟋蟀のようですね
Correct.
ご明察
伊賀の霧隠才蔵
Kirigakure Saizou, of Iga.
まさか本当に会えるなんてね
I never thought I'd meet you.
皆　下がってなさい
Everyone, stand back.
I will defeat him!
こいつは　私が倒す
その「苦無」
That kunai...
同じ伊賀の忍びか
Are you also an Iga ninja?
拙者のことを知っているようだが
You seem to know me,
「様」を付け忘れているぞ　クズ蟲女
but you forgot the "-sama," maggot-girl.
月島　見てなさいよ　これが私の戦い
Tsukishima, watch...
This is how I fight.
い　いなくなちゃった
I-It vanished...
Girl!
嬢ちゃん
我らが目指すのは幸村ただ一人
Our sole goal is Yukimura.
それを忘れてはなりません
Do not forget that.
But...
けどよ
恋川殿　今のうちに
Koikawa-dono, let's go while we can.
Fine, let's go.
分かったよ
成敗
Farewell.
Tsukishima-style: Mt. Fuji Hammer!
月島流　富嶽鉄槌割り
な　何
Wh-What?
I never thought
まさか　こんな腑抜けた江戸の世に
I'd see such a samurai in this
decadent land of Edo...
これほどの武士がこれありそうろうとは
これまでか
Is this the end?
Wh-What?
な　何と　変身した
He transformed?
お許し願いそうろう　お館様
My lord, I beg your forgiveness
ネズミ如きに　この身を曝した弱気拙者を
for being so weak as to
reveal myself to a mere rat!
必ず腹を切ってお詫び申しそうろう
I shall apologize by committing seppuku.
But...
だが
He's much faster than when he was a bug...
蟲の時より格段のスピード
Before I do, I shall take this rat with me!
腹を切る前にネズミを一匹葬りそうろう
Don't imagine that being on land
will give you an advantage.
陸であれば己の利になると思いそうろうや
愚かでこれありそうろう
That would be foolish.
Water God's Army.
水神猛軍
な　何と
Wh-What?
水の流れはわが意のまま
Water is mine to control.
これぞ十傑蟲根津甚八が奥義にでござそうろう
This is the secret technique of Nedzu
Jinpachi, of the Ten Crucifix Insects!
What?
何と
水を思いのままに操る
He can control water?
Then...
ならば
You cannot escape my technique.
わが技から逃れられること　これを得ずにそうろう
水神猛軍
Water God's Army!
What?
何と
Tsukishima-style: Mt. Fuji—
月島流　富嶽
月島
Tsukishima...
貴様との勝負は楽しいでそうろう
Fighting you is so enjoyable.
古きあの時代を思い出す
It reminds me of the old days.
それに引きかえ　今の武士には失望しそうろう
I have been very disappointed
with this era's samurai...
They are ugly and weak, only interested
in flaunting their position.
身分ばかり威張りちらすだけの　あまりに脆弱で醜い存在
Decadent and rotten to the core.
まさに腐ってござそうろう
だが貴様からは　拙者が生まれいずれ戦場の
But in you, I feel the heat of the battlefield
武士の熱を感じござそうろう
whence I was birthed...
However, it is a useless heat.
無駄な熱さではこれありそうろう
流れあるところ拙者に敵うべくもなく
You cannot beat me anywhere that water flows.
水の高きより低きに流れる道理さえ知らず
And you do not even realize that
it flows from high to low ground.
The flow of the water...
水の　流れ
Please, Father...
後生です　父上
山嵐について　一言を　お願いします
Give me but a word on how
to use the Mt. Fuji Storm!
ち　父上　何卒
F-Father, please!
仁兵衛　一つだけ教えてやる
Jinbei, I'll give you one hint.
Listen...
よいか
山嵐最大のコツは流れを読み　つかむことである
The Mt. Fuji Storm's most important part
is to read the flow and grab it!
Read the flow and grab it, huh?
流れを読み　つかむ
苦しみから解いてやるもまた恩情
I shall release you from your suffering.
これでしまいそうろう
This is the end.
久々に骨があったぞ
You were my toughest opponent in a long time.
水神猛軍
Water God's Army!
月島流
Tsukishima-style:
Mt. Fuji...
富嶽
Storm!
山嵐
Wh-What is this?
こ　これは
わが水神猛軍の流れを　逆に利用するとは
He's using the flow of my Water
God's Army to his advantage?
Everything in this world has a flow.
この世のすべてには　流れがある
The river has a flow.
川には川の
The fire has its own.
炎には炎の
嵐には嵐の
The storm, its own.
そして懺撃には懺撃の
And a sword strike, as well.
すべて意志ある流れが存在する
Each of these flows has its own will.
そう
Yes...
月島流　富嶽山嵐とは
The role of the Tsukishima-style Mt. Fuji Storm
元来は相手の懺撃の流れを読み取り　要を受け流す
is a counter-technique that reads
the flow of your opponent's strike,
so you can knock it away.
返しの技である
He who masters the fourth of
Mt. Fuji's thirty-six blades,
富嶽三十六剣　序列第四
the Mt. Fuji Storm,
富嶽山嵐を極めし者こそ
戦場でのすべての流れを掌握可能とする
can control every flow on the battlefield.
月島流
Tsukishima-style:
Rising Dragon!
昇り龍
I c-cannot believe a mere rat defeated me.
ま　まさかこの拙者がネズミ如きにやられそうろうとは
But do not get arrogant, rat.
だが　のぼせるでないぞ　ネズミ共
拙者など所詮十傑蟲六番で
I am but the sixth among
the Ten Crucifix Insects.
雑兵に等しい存在でこれありそうろう
I am only a foot soldier.
他の者達　特に十傑蟲筆頭　霧隠才蔵様をはじめ
The others—especially our leader,
Kirigakure Saizou-sama,
the second, Yuri Kamanosuke-dono,
二番手の由利鎌之介殿
そして三番手筧十蔵殿がこの先に控え致しおりそうそう
and the third, Kakei Juuzou-dono—all await...
As a samurai, I am still inexperienced,
自分は　武士としてまだまだですが
but your fighting was splendid.
根津殿の戦い　見事でした
貴様
You...
先を急がねばならぬみ
I must hurry...
Farewell.
これにて　ごめん
I am so sorry, master.
お館様　申し訳これなくそうろう
あなた様をお慕い長く仕えましたが　ここまでのようでそうろう
I have served and respected you for many years,
but this appears to be the end...
く　口惜しいよ
I am f-filled with regret...
なれど　今のようの武士も　なかなかにでござそうろう
But the samurai of this era are
stronger than I had believed.
Tsukishima Jinbei...
月島仁兵衛
Everyone, where have you gotten lost?
皆さん　どこを迷子になってらっしゃるんですか
火鉢殿
Hibachi-dono!
Ten Crucifix Insects
Kirigakure Saizou
Next Time
I can't believe Hibachi-dono got caught...
火鉢殿が捕まるなんて信じられません
さては偽者
You must be a fake.
Hibachi-dono, if that's really you,
please name your ninjutsu style!
火鉢殿　あなたが本物なら　忍術の流派名をお答えください
Ch-Ch-Chin...
ち　ち　ちん　っていえるか
I can't say it!
次回　蟲奉行「胡蝶の夢」
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
Dream of the Butterfly.